For today uh we're going to be talking
about autonomous learning uh
specifically in the context of
reinforcement learning for robots. Uh
and this lecture and the next lecture
are going to be focusing a bit more on
robotics use cases. Uh where where today
we're going to be talking about autonomy
and on Wednesday we'll be talking about
we have a guest lecture talking about
simtoreal transfer and humanoid robots.
Uh so we'll be talking about uh why
robots aren't autonomous already. Uh
defining the problem of autonomous
reinforcement learning uh and then
developing the algorithms uh
specifically thinking about learning
policies without human intervention and
a formulation of reinforcement learning
uh called single life reinforcement
learning.
Um so uh the goal here will be to think
about how we can imbue uh intelligent
machines with autonomy uh the ability to
allow them to on their own learn
interact practice get better without
human uh without a human in the loop.
Cool. Um so
let's start with some of the um
motivation. So we've been talking a lot
about reinforcement learning. Uh we also
talked a little bit about imitation
learning uh where imitation learning
typically we are training an agent to
mimic some demonstrations that are
provided from an expert whereas in
reinforcement learning the agent is
practicing through trial and error. Uh
and this sort of notion of practicing is
something that is already more
autonomous because the agent is learning
from its own experience in the world. uh
but it actually isn't entirely
autonomous in practice when you think
about running these algorithms on
physical robots. Uh and in particular uh
if we think about saying that we want
some robot that's going from some
initial state distribution uh some
distribution over uh initial uh states.
So this is kind of the starting
conditions that our agent might be faced
with when it's actually deployed uh to
some uh to some kind of region of the
state space that has high reward. Uh
then typically when we think about this
this learning process we will collect
trials. Uh so for example uh maybe at
the beginning the first attempt at the
task will look something like this. uh
where because we are haven't learned
anything yet, maybe we haven't practiced
very much, we don't have a trajectory
that is very good. Um and then from
there, um typically we've thought about
okay, can we retry the task and attempt
the task again where we again start from
um a state in our initial state
distribution and uh kind of roll out our
policy again.
Now when we're rolling out these
policies, we are um kind of sampling
actions from our policy distribution and
uh acting according to the agent's own
actions. And so each of these
trajectories are under the control of uh
of the robot or the agent.
And as you're rolling out your policy,
this part is fully autonomous. it's kind
of fully uh control is fully with the
policy pi.
But one thing kind of one little catch
is that after you've attempted the task
once uh you're in a state over here and
we've been thinking about when you then
attempt the task again magically you'll
somehow get back over here and attempt
the task from this starting place. uh
and we haven't really talked about like
how do you get uh from here all the way
back to here. And [snorts] in practice
when you take kind of traditional
reinforcement learning algorithms that
we've been talking about uh we've been
assuming that a human uh or or somehow
you'll magically get reset to this
initial starting place and in practice
that mean that might mean that a human
is actually uh physically moving the
robot or physically moving the objects
in the scene back to some set of initial
conditions. And as a result, this
process isn't actually fully autonomous.
Um so um on the slides, we'll execute
actions from our policy, observe data
from the environment, update our policy,
repeat that process,
and um eventually we'll get a policy
that is able to get high reward. For
example, in this problem, uh reaching a
state within um some region of goal
states.
And we think about that as rolling out
some uh trajectory of length h and then
rolling out another trajectory of length
length h and so forth. Um but we need to
think about like how do we get from the
end of one trajectory to the start of
another trajectory.
Now if we're in a simulationbased
environment uh then what we can do is we
can create the environment take actions
for a thousand time steps and then once
we're done then we can uh call env.reset
uh which is a very nice little friendly
utility. Uh but that's something that we
can only really do in simulation. We
can't uh kind of reset the physical
world uh to our own will.
Um, and so as some specific examples,
say that you are trying to learn how to
navigate to a basketball court. Maybe
you have a small mobile robot that is
trying to deliver something to the
basketball court or an autonomous
vehicle that's trying to navigate to the
basketball court. Um, as it tries to
explore and attempt this task, it might
make a wrong turn. and rather um if it
makes that sort of wrong turn, it ends
up in that physical location uh and
would need to for example uh figure out
how to navigate either back to the
starting position or find its way from
um from that wrong turn back to where
the basketball truly is.
Um if we have a robot manipulator, we
might want to learn how to grasp the
mug. As we're learning how to grasp the
mug, uh the robot might make a mistake
and knock the mug over. Uh and then if
it wants to attempt and learn how to
grasp things again, then somehow uh it
needs to be within reach of the robot.
Um or if we're kind of more of a mobile
uh mobile system and we want to learn
how to put books on bookshelves
again um we might uh make some mistakes
and need to figure out how to uh kind of
get back to some starting position where
uh the book is in reach or some kind of
initial state distribution. if our goal
is to go from one set of initial states
to uh regions with high reward.
Okay. Um and one of the reasons why this
is actually especially important is that
reinforcement learning often takes many
attempts. It's not a matter of taking
like trying three times and then solving
the task. Often times there's many
different trials that you'll be
attempting and practicing over and over
again. And every time uh the agent tries
again, that means that you have some
human intervention or some other
intervention that is bringing you back
to the initial state distribution.
Okay. Um as more kind of uh real
examples, uh this video on the left uh
is a video of a robot learning how to uh
hit a hockey puck into a goal. And you
can see that uh the uh human here, this
is a friend of mine, Yvan, he's uh
probably doing more work than the robot
is right now uh as it attempts to to do
this. Um here's another example where
Ali is closing the doors so that the
robot can learn how to open them. Um,
and here's an example where Archet uh
who uh you gave a guest lecture earlier
this quarter uh is resetting the robot
so that it can attempt to fold uh fold
the uh the towel.
[snorts]
Okay. So, how do we think about this
problem?
The problem is this sort of reset often
in practice requires some sort of human
intervention that we want to be able to
ideally eliminate so that our agents can
practice and get better on their own
rather than requiring some expert or
some human.
Um now one way that we could look at
this is I mean what if we could just
increase h what if we just increase the
length of the episodes in which our
agents are attempting the task and if we
increase the length of the episodes then
in principle we won't require as much
human supervision and we might be able
to apply the same exact reinforcement
learning algorithms that we've learned
about in the course uh just with uh with
less supervision during the learning
process.
Um, so we can do that. Um, and so, uh,
the we'll see an example of what
increasing age looks like in a minute.
Um, but generally kind of the definition
of what we want to accomplish is
initialize, uh, the scene, the
environment. Maybe it's already
initialized in some way. Then we do that
once we have the agent interact
autonomously with the world um, without
any sort of environment resets. uh we
could also relax this constraint
occasionally um to only reset at a very
low frequency for example if h is very
large.
Now
as we start to think about these systems
we need to think about how we actually
want to evaluate these systems and
there's actually a couple different ways
there's actually a couple different
things that we might care about. So um
one thing that we might care about is
after we've uh for example autonomously
uh learned in some environment um we
might care about uh maybe let's kind of
well
let's say that we've uh autonomously
explored uh and for example we have um
kind of some uh uh experience that we've
collected uh maybe that looks something
like this.
uh where there's no resets, no kind of
going back to the initial state.
Um one thing that we might care about is
we might care about did you achieve high
reward as you kind of went about um the
agent's experience and basically did it
actually complete the task at the end of
the day as it was learning and that
would be looking at like what is the sum
of uh the rewards that it accomplished
over its lifetime.
Um, and alternatively, instead of
thinking about evaluating autonomous RL
from that perspective, we could think
about after the learning process, did we
learn a good policy that we could then
deploy and be able to repeatedly do the
task? Um, and so that would be looking
at um like if we instead of looking at
the rewards of this red trajectory, it
would be saying after the learning
process, if we've learned some policy,
um how well how good is it at, for
example, going to the goal? how good is
the policy that it learned um as an
outcome of the reinforcement learning
process.
Um so two things here. One could be the
amount of reward recovered over the
course of its life. As [clears throat]
one example of this uh imagine that
you're deploying the Mars rover uh and
you want the rover to be able to collect
scientific data. the you don't really
care about whether it learned a good
policy that you're going to deploy uh in
um in like after the learning process.
You really care about whether or not it
did a good job uh as it was deployed as
it was learning and so forth. Uh so
that's more like like trying to measure
how good is this red trajectory.
Um, and so this here's my graphical
depiction of this on on the slide. Um,
or you could learn about the quality of
the learn policy. An example of this is
that if you're learning how to cook
meals, maybe there's some sort of
training process. um you don't really
care that much about during the training
process how well um it was able to cook
as it was learning but then you really
care about then can I deploy the system
and have it be able to uh cook meals
effectively uh repeatedly for a variety
of customers in the future.
Cool. So that would be kind of a typical
like if we kind of then took a policy
that we learned initialized it at the
starting state uh and ran it um does it
achieve good reward under those
conditions.
Um so we'll think about these as two
different things. So we can
um first let's think about what we'll
call like deployed policy evaluation. So
how good is the policy that we learned
if we were to then deploy it? And the
objective for this circumstance can be
defined as uh an objective that looks
very similar to what we've been um
seeing in the course previously, which
is that you would sample a state from
your initial state distribution and act
according to your policy
and measure the sum of rewards or the
sum of discounted rewards
that was observed after starting after
running an episode um this should be
yeah an expectation um after starting
from the state and uh acting according
to the policy
um so this is deployed policy evaluation
um how good is the policy if it's
starting from the initial state
distribution and acting according to the
policy
alternatively uh if we were to think
about more like the uh kind of
continuing policy evaluation how good
are we if we kind of just deploy the
system and it's trying to learn um as it
as it goes and how good is it during
that learning process, then we'd
actually be considering something a
little bit different. Uh the we would
want to be considering what is the
average reward that it saw during um
during that learning process. And so we'
be looking at something like um the
uh
some uh kind of average quantity. So
we'll call um we'll write this as 1 / h
if t = 1 to h of the
uh reward.
And
we
um if h is small this is not this is be
averaged over a small thing. And so we
want to be evaluating this um usually as
our lifetime might be getting longer and
longer. So this would be um a limit kind
of evaluating average reward in the
limit uh in which h goes to infinity.
So something like this um and there
should be uh an expectation over um over
this quantity. Now this expectation
isn't necess isn't under a single
policy. Uh it's over the learning
process itself. Uh so that's another
difference from measuring how good a
learn policy is.
Cool. Um and so we'll look at algorithms
for both these circumstances.
Yeah. So the question is why do we need
an expectation if we're just like uh
running one trajectory? Um the
if you want to like evaluate just like a
single like lifetime or a single um roll
out of your learning process then you
could just like measure exa precisely
that like run it and see how well it
does. Now in practice um there's
variability that's caused by variability
in the environment variability in your
learning process uh like like how you
sample batches and so forth. And uh you
may want to measure like at the
algorithm level how good is your
algorithm at um this sort of problem.
And uh if you want to measure how good
the algorithm is, you'll want an
expectation over multiple runs of the
algorithm.
Why is this important? We've already
talked a bit about the motivation. Um
but uh to kind of elaborate on a little
bit more, uh we want robots to operate
with minimal human supervision. Um, but
we also want them to train with minimal
supervision as well. And um,
generally reinforcement learning on real
robots is a kind of a promising path
towards achieving really high success
rates, really high reliability compared
to imitation learning. Um, and if you're
able to train with minimal human
supervision, then you're able to collect
more data. And more data may also unlock
both greater reliability and also
greater generalization. as uh if these
systems are able to be deployed uh at
scale in a variety of real world
environments.
Um so that's the problem setup. Uh now
let's dive a bit into algorithms.
So
uh we like to learn policies without uh
human supervision. And we talked about
this question before of like what if we
just increase the length of the episode
um and can we just take a traditional
kind of standard reinforcement learning
algorithm um in this case I think we'll
be looking at soft actor critic and just
run it with longer and longer episodes
which in principle should require less
and less supervision.
Uh and if we do this um we see
performance changes a bit. So uh this is
a plot that's evaluating how good is the
learned policy after training for some
number of steps shown on the x-axis. So
the y-axis is reward of accomplished by
kind of the deployed policy. So it's
this blue uh measuring this blue
equation right here.
And um this green line is if you run
with an episode length of a thousand
steps. If you run SACE, you get a
learning curve where it's able to learn
a policy that's able to effectively
complete the task.
Now, if you increase uh the length of
the episodes during training uh by a
factor of two, we see that the algorithm
does worse. Uh and then we increase it
uh by a factor of 10, we see that does
even worse. And basically as we increase
and make the episode length longer and
as a result reduce the supervision
required uh for training uh the
algorithm at the very end is is hardly
able to learn uh how to do the task at
all. How to learn how to a policy that
can do the task at all. Um, and I should
mention this is kind of a very simple um
kind of fish control task where your
goal is to navigate uh with uh with what
the fish can do uh to a different uh a
particular position. So pretty simple
task. Um even for this simple task uh if
you increase your episode length and
don't give it resets very frequently,
you're aren't able to learn a good
policy.
Now why is this the case? I guess does
anyone have hypothesis for why like why
we're not getting a good policy uh if we
only reset every like 50,000 steps or
100,000 steps. Yeah. So the first issue
that can happen is it can u make a
mistake and kind of uh do something
that's bad maybe leads it to a part of
the state space that uh is very hard to
recover from. um in this particular
environment I don't think it's possible
for it to break its tail or something
but uh the you can kind of basically
drift away from the state distribution
that's good and so if we were to think
about this um maybe that diagram is
getting a little bit messy our goal is
to learn a policy that goes from some
initial state distribution to uh some
goal as a simple reinforcement learning
problem as we're learning we might
simply kind of deviate uh from the kind
of where the set of good states is and
because of this drift it might be very
hard to recover and get closer to the
parts that have high reward.
Um so that's one challenge. Uh does
anyone else have ideas on another
challenge?
The other challenge is actually a little
bit more nuanced and in particular uh
say that we drift away but maybe um
maybe either in another episode after
one reset or even um for this episode uh
if you are able to eventually get to the
goal uh which is good. You got reward.
Um from there
you might uh simply kind of stay in this
region of the state space
and if you start collecting a lot of
data in this part of the state space
you're getting lots of reward. So you're
you're um kind of the learning process
is great but then if your goal is to
learn a policy um that starts from here
and goes to here uh you're not actually
visiting the states that will uh yield a
good policy.
uh and so the
you might not be visiting the states
that allow you to actually uh kind of go
effectively from one initial state to
the goal.
So two challenges. Um if we think about
this row star as the optimal state
distribution for getting from start to
goal then um in episodic learning you
can always retry the task from the
initial state distribution.
Whereas um in autonomous learning or
non-epodic learning um you'll continue
from where you left off and that sort of
exploration might lead you to drift away
from the set of good states for getting
to the goal. Um, and then even if you do
eventually get to the goal, your state
distribution in your replay buffer might
collapse and um, and might be kind of
concentrated around the goal rather than
capturing the state distribution uh,
that's around the optimal policy. And if
you don't have states from the optimal
policy, you won't know what to do or
what actions to take when you're in this
part of the state space.
Cool. Um and so as an outcome of this
you'll never actually learn a good
policy.
So um how can we learn an effective
policy? Uh so if the agent is allowed to
reset from the initial state
distribution, we do learn successfully.
And so one very simple idea is to try to
learn a policy that brings us from
wherever we ended up after attempting
the task back to the initial state
distribution. Uh and we can call this
idea we can think of this as like a
reset policy or a backwards policy
that's trying to undo the task rather
than uh do the task forward.
Um and so we can think of this as uh
kind of forward backward RL because we
will be learning a forward policy that
does the task and a backward policy that
undoes the task
and h where to put this. Uh
maybe let's do it over here. Uh so
you'll first uh maybe step zero is to
initialize and sample
an initial state from
your initial state distribution.
Basically initializing the agent and
then you're going to repeatedly
run your forward policy which I'll call
pf. then
update your forward policy
uh by trying to maximize uh the sum of
rewards and this will be using the
reward function for completing the task.
I'll call that RF uh the forward reward
function.
And then uh we'll reach some state. we
won't reset and we'll run our backward
policy uh pi b and then we can likewise
update our backward policy
uh this in this case we need to update
it for the reverse of the forward task
and so we'll actually rely on a reward
function that will tell us if we are
reaching the initial state distribution
um and so this is going to require a
second reward function
uh RB that is going to serve as reward
for the backward policy. Uh now in terms
of these update steps, you can use your
favorite reinforcement learning
algorithm for this. Uh
and critically after we run the backward
policy, we're not going to reset. Uh
we'll then kind of go back to running
the forward policy again.
And so what this would look like is we
will define this backward reward
function which is for like rewards us
for reaching states in um in the initial
state distribution. Then we'll
initialize them and repeatedly roll out
the forward policy. Then update the
forward policy with respect to reaching
the goal. Roll out the backward policy
uh which is going to try to go back to
the initial state distribution. then
update the backward policy and then
without resetting again try to roll out
the forward policy, roll out the
backward policy and repeat this process.
Um you can also have a reset very
infrequently. So occasionally um
occasionally reset it just in case it
does kind of get stuck in a really
challenging state.
Um and then at test time uh once you're
done with this process you can discard
the backward policy and just deploy your
forward policy which should have learned
um ideally how to get efficiently from
the uh initial state distribution to the
goal uh or generally to maximize the
forward reward function.
One other small note here is that we're
going to be typically you need to decide
how long to roll out the forward policy
for. The simplest thing to do is simply
to roll it out for h time steps. Uh so
choose a constant number of time steps
to roll it out for. Uh you could imagine
doing something more sophisticated. Uh
for example, before the forward policy
has learned anything, the backward
policy like if it's not moving anywhere,
the backward policy won't really have
any job to do at the beginning. And so
you for example could run this for a
little bit longer at the beginning. Um
but then at some point you'll also need
to run the backward policy for a little
bit longer. Um and it's a bit simpler to
just use a fixed number of steps.
Um and ideally if this process is
autonomous then um the number of time
steps actually matters a little bit less
because uh you can like go to sleep
while your robot is uh trying to learn.
Yeah. So the question is is there any
information sharing between the forward
policy and the backward policy. Uh if
you're using like replay buffers you
could consider sharing data between the
two and reabeling the rewards for the
forward policy for the backward policy
and vice versa. Um
in practice it's fairly common to
actually uh not share much information.
You you could also share like an image
encoder for example um like share some
of the weights uh that can be helpful
but um they are actually trying to learn
in some ways very different things. Uh
and so that makes it a little bit
tricky. We'll also see some algorithms
uh later on that do more sharing.
Okay. So the upside of this algorithm is
quite simple. Um the one of the
downsides is that this backward policy
that's trying to undo the task. Uh
ultimately this is not um not
particularly useful. Uh so the um it's
in some ways it seems a little bit
wasteful to learn this policy. Uh but it
does enable uh kind of this sort of
autonomous learning which is quite nice.
So this is kind of like the the most
simple algorithm you could use for
trying to learn autonomously. Uh but
there are also some alternatives that uh
in some ways have a number of appealing
properties. Uh so first uh when you're
for your backward policy um you can
actually change the reward function that
it uses uh to actually not reset to all
the way back to the beginning but
potentially to reset from a a larger
variety of states.
Um, second, we could instead of learning
forward and backward just for one task,
we could think about practicing a cycle
of different tasks. Um, and not just
learning kind of a forward task and a
backward task. We'll talk about that a
bit. Um, and then the other option is
you could also set up a task that can be
done repeatedly where you can just kind
of keep on attempting the task over and
over again um, in kind of certain
special circumstances. Uh, and we'll
talk about that briefly as well.
Um, cool. Let's first talk about
learning to reset to a different initial
state distribution from the initial
state. And so the motivation here is
that um in forward backward we're kind
of trying the task going back trying the
task going back. And the
um ultimately we want to be able to do
complete the task from the initial state
distribution. Uh but we also like need
to know how to take good actions all
along the expert state distribution as
well.
And so one of the things that we could
do is instead of going back all the way
to the beginning every single time uh we
could actually reset um two different
states along the expert uh state
distribution.
And uh there's actually work that shows
that um if you were to do this and had a
way to do this then you'd actually learn
a bit more efficiently than always
starting from the initial state
distribution even in episodic learning
settings. Uh and so uh the way that this
works is it's basically going to be the
same exact thing as before. Um but with
like basically like two small
modifications.
Uh and the first is that if we want to
be able to reset and learn a policy that
brings us to the expert state
distribution, then we need a way to
approximate what that expert state
distribution is. And so we'll assume
that we have a few demonstrations.
And so uh maybe step negative one here
is uh you're basically given uh some set
of expert
trajectories or expert demonstrations
and these will be examples of ways to
accomplish the task.
And then you need to change the reward
function for the backward policy where
the reward function shouldn't be to
reach the initial state distribution but
instead it should be to reach uh to
reach states that the expert visits.
And so in particular we'll be given a
small set of demonstrations. And ideally
what we want this to look like is we'd
run our forward policy and then we when
we run our backward policy um after it's
uh kind of learned something reasonable
ideally it would kind of just bring us
back to the set of um the set of states
in the expert distribution. Um then we
run our forward policy again and then it
would bring us back again somewhere in
this pink region that is showing uh the
distribution of states that are visited
by the expert.
Um
and so uh the forward backward process
is the same uh but we have this modified
backward reward function and uh we're
actually going to learn this reward
function.
uh and in particular we talked about in
the lecture on learning reward functions
how you can uh train discriminators to
discriminate between good states and bad
states and use states from the policy as
examples of bad states. And we can do
the same exact thing here where this
reward function will be trained to
distinguish states visited by the policy
and states visited in the
demonstrations. Uh and then you'll be
trying to uh when you're training the
the backward policy, you'll be trying to
trick this reward function into thinking
that the states it's visiting are states
from the expert and not from the policy.
Um, and then again we'll discard our
backward policy when we're done and
deploy our forward policy.
Um, cool. So assume some demonstrations,
run our forward policy, backward policy
and so forth. Um, this um this and
forward backward RL addresses the
challenge of preventing the agent from
drifting away and it also avoids
collapsing the distribution um that we
talked about before as well.
>> [snorts]
>> Cool. And then the upside that we that I
mentioned very briefly is that if you
try the task from a wide set of initial
states um both easier states like states
that are closer to the goal and further
states then you could actually improve
the efficiency of the entire
reinforcement learning algorithm.
The [snorts] last thing that I'll
mention is that you can actually use
these demonstrations um in the like
replay buffers um as data to help train
the forward policy and the reverse
policy as well. So the question is uh if
the agent finishes the task um does the
backward policy just stay there? Uh and
here the example the the answer is no.
So in the case of forward backwardl it
would go back to the initial state
whereas in the case of um this kind of
metal algorithm it'll kind of try to
push the policy to a state in the expert
state distribution and the um
specifically when we're training uh the
classifier to classify between policy
states and expert states we're using all
of the states in the trajectories all
the states in in the demos. Uh and so
it's going to for example um like in
this graphic go back to somewhere over
here um so that the policy then learns
uh and practices how to do the task from
here rather than only practicing it from
the goal state. Right? The question is
what prevents it from actually staying
in the goal state because the goal state
is part of the demonstrations. Uh the
the specifics of
I was thinking about not going into
this, but basically the specifics of
this reward function is actually kind of
a a state distribution matching
objective where its goal is to match the
um the states that it visits with the
states in the demos. And if it only uh
resets to the goal state, then the
classifier or the the discriminator this
reward function will learn that if
you're only in the goal state, then
that's probably coming from the policy
and not from the expert demos. Uh and
the it will be able to yeah distinguish
that. Um and the way that you can kind
of formalize that is you can actually um
think about it as a divergence between
the states the distribution of states
visited by the backward policy and the
distribution of states visited by the
experts.
Cool. So um let's actually briefly look
at how these algorithms perform. So um
there's actually a benchmark for uh kind
of this sort of autonomous uh
reinforcement learning setting um called
Earl. And during training you only get a
reset every 200,000
environment steps. So very infrequently
and the evaluation is how good is the
policy when you start it from some
initial state distribution. Um the
benchmark has a few different tasks.
This is probably the simplest task in
the benchmark where you can um basically
try to like grab a cup and move it. Um
and there's this very simple grabbing
mechanism um that makes the task
simpler. Uh and then we'll also look at
a more complex task on the next slide.
Um and if we look at what different
algorithms do in this environment where
they only get uh resets every 200,000
steps. Um, first if we just run SACE uh
without a backward policy uh where it
only gets very infrequent resets like we
saw with the fish, the performance isn't
very good and it doesn't learn a good
forward policy.
Um, if we use an oracle that is able to
get resets um much more frequently, then
it is actually able to learn a good
policy.
And then there's a few algorithms um
kind of reset free algorithms. uh one is
something that tries to perturb it and
encourage it to visit novel states. Um
another shown in orange is kind of the
vanilla forward backward reinforcement
learning algorithm.
Um we can also give it some sort of goal
curriculum. Um I didn't talk
specifically about this algorithm. Um
and then the blue algorithm um is the
algorithm that's trying to uh reset back
to states in the demonstrations.
Um and so we see that uh first I guess
the kind of main takeaway here is that
these algorithms um that are
specifically designed for this kind of
autonomous or reset-free learning
setting are able to do much better than
if you don't design it for that case. Um
and in this simple environment they all
perform kind of fairly similarly. Uh and
then as we move towards more complex
environments um we see that forward
backward RL uh and metal um are able to
kind of do the best whereas simply if
you instead try to kind of encourage it
to visit various um states or goals uh
those algorithms aren't doing quite as
well. Yeah the question is um we're
assuming some expert trajectories how
are those um generated? So, uh there's a
variety of ways that you can generate
them. Um on a real robot, you would
typically use some sort of teley
operation device. Uh and that could be
um using like um like a a puppeteering
like setup or a VR controller or a 3D
mouse or a keyboard. Um, in simulation,
uh, it can either be something that's
like a scripted policy, um, that is like
designed by a person or it could be a
policy that's like trained with RL, um,
ahead of time just to test, uh, the
algorithms. Can I describe what the
episodic part is? So, um, episodic is a
term that often refers to like the
traditional reinforcement learning
setting where we can attempt the task
and reset and attempt the task again
where each thing is like each attempt is
like an episode. And so it's like very
episodic. You get one episode, you try
again, you get another episode. Um, and
then it's not the not the best term, but
that's that's one term. And then um
non-epodic refers to the setting where
you don't get those resets. You just let
it go. Um, and so it's not it's it's no
longer like a bunch of episodes. is just
like one long uh learning process.
Uh sometimes that learning process is
also called reset free uh because there
are no resets in the process.
Oh, the other thing that I should
mention actually that's kind of cool
about this particular task is um the
forward task is to close the door and
the backward task is to open the door
and the backward task is actually um
depending on where the arm starts can
actually be quite a bit harder than the
forward task. And so you could sometimes
have these sort of mismatches between
how hard it is to do the forward task
and how hard it is to do the backward
task. And that can make these algor that
can generally um sometimes make the
learning process a bit more challenging
because the forward policy and the
backward policy will learn at different
rates. Um similarly, if you could
imagine like um if your forward task is
like to do a backflip for example, uh
maybe doing a back flip is really
challenging but like getting up and
standing up to start doing the back flip
is is comparably easier. Um and so
that's it's kind of fairly common to
have a mismatch in that sort of
difficulty.
Um these sorts of algorithms have also
like they're you can actually run them
on real robots and it's kind of cool.
You can like watch time lapses of them.
Uh the left video is running a forward
backward RL where it's learning a
forward policy learning a backward
policy and you can see that both
policies kind of make mistakes. Um and
it's able to uh I don't know if you can
see it in the context of this single
video but um it is able to improve just
by kind of um through kind of a fully
autonomous process. And then the right
is um the metal algorithm. And you can
see that like for example um if the
forward policy uh misses then the
backward policy doesn't really have much
to do. Um and so you do see uh yeah that
another property of the algorithm uh in
the video.
Cool. Um one other thing that I'll
mention is that rewards are also
something that the real world doesn't
provide. Uh and so using reward learning
algorithms in conjunction with
autonomous or reset free algorithms um
is also quite common. And in both of
these circumstances the rewards were
using models rather than using humans.
uh so that this entire process can be
kind of autonomous and um like you can
actually like run it overnight for
example. Yeah. So the question is um it
seems like for some of these tasks like
if you don't have a good backward policy
then it's really hard to learn the
forward policy and also vice versa like
if you don't have a good forward policy
um then you're never actually going to
be picking up the towel and then you
need to figure out uh like how to um
then you're you're not really getting
actually any good states. Uh the in
general one of the things you can do is
you can provide demonstrations both for
the forward task and for the backward
task um and use that to help bootstrap
the learning process for both of them.
Um the other than that um it is just
generally a challenge and to uh yeah to
try to balance these two things and um
yeah in general the algorithms are are
able to work uh in some settings. Uh I
should also mention that like these
works um works that are doing these like
um
they're kind of still I mean certainly
still in like the research stages I
think uh this is not something that like
uh that like robot companies are using
uh today. Yeah.
Cool. Um so we've talked about kind of
algorithms that learn a reset policy to
help learning a forward policy. Now, um,
we could also think about a slightly
different setting, which is that if
we're trying to learn not just one task,
but multiple tasks, then we could
actually think about not just kind of
going forward and backward, but
practicing like kind of going in cycles
and practicing different tasks depending
on what state you're in. So, for
example, if you have a robot that's
trying to make coffee, maybe the first
task is to put or or the first subtask
is to put the cup in the coffee machine.
Um, and maybe if it attempts that, it
actually like drops the cup on accident.
Uh, and then kind of traditionally what
you would do is you would have a human
uh kind of reset the cup back to where
it started. Uh, but we don't want to do
that. And so, um, instead maybe the
second task is, um, instead of because
it made a mistake, the second task
shouldn't be to like turn on the coffee
machine. Instead, it should be to pick
up the cup.
Um, and so we can imagine having these
different cycles where we practice task
one. Uh, then if we fail, we practice
task two. And then, uh, task two maybe
is kind of resetting task one. We maybe
then go back to task one, which is to
put the cup in the coffee machine. If we
uh didn't succeed at task two, we might
keep trying it. U if we do succeed at
task one at putting in the coffee
machine, we might move to task three. Um
and and so on and so forth. Uh and so we
could have this sort of graph or cycle
of different tasks that we're trying.
And at different points in time,
depending on the state we're in, we'll
practice a different task that is
possible to practice from that state and
exclude tasks that are not feasible from
that state. [snorts] Cool.
So, uh what this would look like is we
will be learning a task condition
policy. So, like a multitask policy and
the
we will be in
uh some state and so we'll observe uh
the state that we're in. And then based
on the state that we're in, we'll
propose a task that we want to practice
from that state. So we'll have a step
that is proposing a task that we can use
uh zi to denote the task that we're
proposing.
Uh [snorts] and this would this could be
like the descriptor for that task. And
then we will
uh run the policy for that task.
Uh, and so this could be a multitask
policy.
Uh, whoops.
That's conditioned on ZI.
And then we could also have an update
step where we update our policy. Uh, if
we have a more on policy algorithm, then
this would be updating it for this
particular task. If we have an off
policy algorithm, uh, we could update it
for any of the tasks. and then repeat
this process where after we've run it
for that task for some number of steps,
we'll then propose a different task and
practice that task.
So, initialize our policy, propose a
task, uh roll out the policy for eight
steps and then update um and
specifically we'll be updating it with
the reward function uh for uh that that
takes into account the tasks that we're
practicing. And so, we'll need a reward
function for all of the tasks that we
might be doing.
Um yeah and then again we won't have uh
resets or we'll have a very infrequent
reset.
Um and then uh at test time we can then
deploy this multitask policy which can
do not just one task but multiple
different tasks.
Um and as an example uh this is a robot
system that is um the goal is to pick up
this basically has different stages and
different tasks are different stages.
you want to pick up um this object uh
flip it over and rotate it. Uh and there
are different subtasks here. And so at
the beginning it doesn't know how to
flip it and it doesn't certainly doesn't
know how to rotate it. um or maybe it
maybe it does actually know how to to
flip it, but it isn't very good at
rotating it is something where at the
beginning you don't know how to flip it
or rotate it. And you'll basically just
be like practicing picking it up from
the hand uh and putting it back, picking
it up, putting it um putting it back,
putting it down. Um and then once you
get better at picking it up, then you'll
start to actually uh kind of rotate it
or flip it over and rotate it. Um and so
depending on which state you're actually
in, you'll actually practice something
that makes sense for that given state.
And this can actually address some of
the challenges um that we talked about
with regard to imbalance in tasks where
if you haven't actually yet like run
successfully run the forward policy uh
to actually change the state and you may
not even be in a state where it makes
sense to run the backward policy then
you can keep on running uh the the um
the policy for a task that makes sense.
Um as a couple examples more examples of
this uh this um example on the left
you're trying to learn both for running
walking forward and walking backwards
and um also you also at the same time
are actually learning how to get back
up. Uh and so you can see it kind of
transitioning between going forward
going backward. Um if it's too far to
the back then it'll uh then it will
doesn't want to keep on going backwards.
And so then you'll practice the task of
going forwards.
Um, and likewise this example on the
right, there's actually it's like a
sevenstage task where you need to pick
it up um position it uh and like screw
uh repeatedly. And so it's running these
different policies or these different
controllers uh based on the state that
it's in. Um and eventually it will also
run kind of the backward policy of
putting the wrench back on the table.
Yeah. Yeah. So the question is like how
do we select these tasks basically? Um
yeah so there's basically kind of two
two approaches that have been done here
and this is also kind of like sort of at
the bleeding edge of research in some
ways. Um the first is that you could
predefine a set of tasks and also
predefine that graph saying like if you
failed task one then you should go to
you should practice task two and
physically at upfront predefine that
graph what you should do in different
circumstances. um and then act according
to that graph. Um alternatively, uh you
could also kind of [clears throat] train
a model that proposes tasks for you to
do. Uh and so um for example, in
general, I think it's kind of an open
question with regard to like which task
you pick to collect for at a given point
in time. Uh but you could for example
ask a language model to say like what
are the different things that I could do
in this environment to get better and
actually then practice the task that it
describes as output. Um and so as an
example of that um if we are at um if
this is the kind of the frame that we're
in then there's certain things that we
can do in this task. We could like open
this toy microwave. We could pick up the
banana. We could like push the eggplant
move the pot. Um, but if we instead told
it to like pick up the carrot, uh,
that's not something that you can do in
the scene. Uh, and if if we're trying to
actually train it to do lots of
different things, the these tasks are be
scene dependent. [snorts] Uh, so then
you could ask, uh, a a VLM that to
understand like think about what are the
things that you can do in this
environment and then have it predict,
for example, take the banana out of the
silver pot. Um and then from there
actually have it practice doing this
task versus uh um practicing doing some
other task. Uh the question is how is
this different from hierarchical
learning? So the
it's a good question. So this task
proposer you can sort of think of it
like it shares some similarities with
the highle policy that's telling you
what to do in a certain circumstance. Uh
but its purpose is actually quite
different. So uh the purpose here is
actually in uh having it propose things
that you could do in the environment
that you could practice. Uh whereas in a
hierarchal system um the high level
policy goal is to say like what is the
next subtask that will achieve some
outcome at the end of the day. Uh and so
this is actually something where you
want it to give you lots of different
things that allow you to learn lots of
different things. Um whereas a high
level policy you're much more goal-
directed in terms of accomplishing some
sort of long-term objective.
Um this particular work uh chooses to um
actually use a hierarchal method. Um
it's sort of actually it kind of uh
builds upon the one of the works that we
talked about previously where it
actually then feeds this um into an
image editing diffusion model to
generate an image of a generated goal
and then um it trains the policy to try
to reach this goal image. Um uh and one
of the things that's nice about this is
that with this sort of approach, you
need to update this using a reward
function for each task. And it can be
quite challenging to define a reward
function for all of the different tasks.
Uh whereas if you have an image of the
task that you're trying to accomplish,
then your reward function can be based
on whether or not um you're close to
this image. And so it makes it easier to
define the reward functions. Your
question is um would this proposer like
kind of give those outputs?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So absolutely. So this um
this sort of framework was applied to
like these simple robot scenes, but you
could also for example like in the
hockey example ask it like what are the
things I could do in this situation?
Should I like practice passing? Should I
practice shooting? Um, for those
particular examples, I think it's also
reasonable to just like there's only
like a limited things limited number of
things that you need to practice and so
you could just have one session on
practicing goals, one session on on on
passing. Uh, but yeah, you could also
use an idea like this to actually
propose um what to try to do in
different situations.
Those are a couple autonomous learning
algorithms. The first category being
like algorithms where you try to do the
task and then kind of undo the task in
various ways. the second where you're
trying to then kind of try to do one
task and then another task and then
another task and trying to just get
better at lots of different tasks all at
once. Um there's also actually some
scenarios where you can actually set up
the task in a way that you can do it
repeatedly. Uh and the there isn't um
necessarily a lot of research on on this
particular idea. But in this particular
example, the goal is to uh fold napkins
uh for um businesses where you need to
fold lots of napkins. So those are all
circumstances where we want to learn a
policy uh and we like our goal is to get
a good policy um rather than simply uh
kind of the Mars rover example where we
want to maximize rewards. Uh there's
also the second category of problems.
Uh and uh the motivation is that um
we've been trying to learn policies
without resets. you can improve the
quality of the policy through practice.
Uh but then at some point we're actually
going to be deploying the policy and
ideally this policy will be pretty good
and um maybe you're in a scenario where
obviously like everything is going to
work perfectly. Nothing will ever go
wrong when you actually go and deploy
your policy. Uh but in practice that's
not the case. Uh and the natural world
uh things will go wrong uh despite
having a lot of training. Uh, and this
ladder setting is thinking about after
we've learned some sort of policy, uh,
when it's out in the world on its own,
can it recover from mistakes and learn,
uh, kind of after the deployment
process?
Um, and this is something that even
humans do to some extent. So, uh, here's
a video where a person is trying to open
a door. Uh, and if you look really
carefully, you'll notice that actually
the person makes a mistake. uh and then
adapts uh really like in really in like
a split second in order to accomplish
the task. Um so if we play this video
again, we'll see that right here um the
person is trying to apply force and the
key actually isn't correctly in the hole
and then they um kind of try again by
removing the key backwards and then
putting it back into the keyhole. Um,
and there's lots of examples like this
um, hopefully that you've encountered
uh, in uh, in your own deployed policy.
Um, and we'd like to think about this
setting where we could actually adapt
within an episode uh, during deployment.
So in terms of how this compares to
previous algorithms, we've talked about
like a lot of the course has been
talking about this episodic setting
where you attempt it from the initial
state repeatedly and then deploy the
policy once. We also talked today about
this reset free setting where you uh
learn how to kind of uh attempt the
task, undo the task repeatedly and then
want to deploy um uh your policy. Uh and
this more recent setting is something
where you have some prior training data.
Maybe you've trained a policy and you're
in some sort of new out of distribution
circumstance and as you're trying to um
actually do the task. Uh because you're
in some new circumstances, you need to
do some problem solving and actually uh
adapt and learn during deployment during
a single episode without resets.
Um, and so you can sort of think of this
as like after kind of previous data or
previous training, you have one life to
autonomously complete the task.
Um, as a fairly simple example, maybe
you have training experience on like in
a flat uh like running in like flat
ground and then at some point you
encounter some obstacle that you haven't
seen before and you need to figure out
how to get over this obstacle despite
not having seen this during training and
you want to use reinforcement learning
or use some ideas from reinforcement
learning to adapt to the new
circumstances live uh within an episode.
So,
one thing we might think about is like
can we just run can we continue to
fine-tune our policy with reinforcement
learning at test time. If for example we
make a mistake like maybe we can just
update our policy with like TD updates
um or policy gradients uh like live as
we're rolling out our policy.
Um,
and so if we if we actually do that, so
we we train a policy and then try to
fine-tune it um at test time with uh
with this sort of obstacle, uh we get
something that looks like this. So uh
the policy actually does figure out how
to get over the first obstacle even
though it has never seen that obstacle
before. Um, and then eventually it
actually kind of gets stuck uh on like
flipped over and even though it's
running reinforcement learning. Um, and
you can see it's kind of it is somewhat
like trying to get up, uh, it
essentially gets stuck. Uh, and even
though you're kind of still running
reinforcement learning, still running
the policy, and still running updates,
uh, it isn't able to recover from these
kinds of states that it hasn't seen
before uh, without like on its own,
without interventions.
And ideally we'd have a policy that
could figure out like how to get up and
how to retry um like during deployment
in these sort of new circumstances.
Now um
this is also something that's like kind
of bleeding edge of research. Uh and
I'll just mention a few ideas that have
been proposed that seem to be quite
helpful for addressing this sort of
problem.
Um, one is that the when you're getting
stuck, you're kind of um you end up in
this state that's hard to recover from.
And if you're doing reinforcement
learning updates, um, say that you uh
are like running your policy and somehow
you get kind of stuck right here. Uh, if
you're running reinforcement learning
updates, you are running reinforcement
updates with regard to the the task of
getting to the goal.
And if instead of trying to run RL
updates to get to the goal, if you
instead tried to run RL updates to kind
of get back to states that are familiar,
like good states that you visited in
your previous experience, then you might
have a better time at getting unstuck
where uh for example, these states might
be closer to the ones that are at the
goal and help perturb the agent kind of
back to something that it knows so that
it could then continue doing the task.
Um, so that's one idea. Um, and then
another idea is to try to leverage
pre-training. So
the if you're trying to run
reinforcement learning on the policy
weights like in the low-level action
space, uh you can only change the policy
so much and there's only so so many ways
you can adapt.
Uh and if instead if you could adapt in
a higher level space like if you had
some set of pre-trained skills then you
might be able to actually adapt more
drastically and actually try to change
change a strategy that you're taking
rather than just changing the weights or
the actions that you're using. Um, so
for example, if you learned a skill for
a kind of a pre-trained skill for
walking forward and a pre-trained skill
for kind of getting back on your feet,
then instead of trying to kind of
continue walk forward in that new state,
if you tried to explore the different
skills that you have and explore the
state of getting back up, then you might
be able to actually be more successful
at handling these sort of circumstances
because you're basically able to try
different strategies rather than just
trying different actions or different
weights.
Um the other thing here is that kind of
pre-trained um LLMs might have some sort
of common sense reasoning that could
allow uh an agent to adapt in novel
circumstances as well and try different
strategies. Um so let's look at a couple
examples of these ideas in practice. Um
so if we take the first idea that's
trying to guide the agent with
reinforcement learning to familiar
states rather than to the goal. Uh we
can actually run it on that same example
and we see that the agent um does
actually I mean this is still an out of
distribution environment. It does get
stuck on its back but it is able to for
example get back up um after some uh
after trying. So here it's stuck on its
back and it's trying to get back to a
state that's familiar. for example, a
state where it's on its feet um and it's
able to eventually recover from that uh
after a bit of attempts uh and then uh
make it to the goal state.
And then in terms of um adopting and we
talked about adopting the low-level
space and in the high level space um
this first example is a system that was
trained uh to be able to adapt uh kind
of in the low-level space from recent
history. Uh, and this is able to handle
kind of some small uh, auto distribution
scenarios where it's like on different
terrains.
Uh, but if you have things that are kind
of more drastically different from what
you've seen before, it could be very
helpful to adapt in a more high level
space.
Uh, and so what that could look like is
say that you um, say that you have this
legged robot that's trying to reach a
goal over here. Then uh if for example
you kind of all the agent sees is is
this uh this image right here tries to
go forward goes backward. If you just
keep on running a policy without any
sort of context, it'll just keep on
trying to go forward because it doesn't
know that um it it kind of tried going
forward before. Um if instead you try
different strategies like moving left uh
moving backwards uh with context and
adaptation then you can figure out um
how to ultimately like even though the
like the agent in this particular case
has never seen this environment before
it's able to kind of problem solve uh
its way through these different
obstacles um and navigating to a goal
position. Um this is something where if
you adapted in like kind of the
low-level motor space like trying out
different like uh different like
positions of your joints then it would
be very tricky to try to problem solve
uh through this sort of circumstance.
Cool. So that was a brief uh foray into
this single life reinforcement learning
setting. Yeah, good question. So um how
do we bacon safety constraints? So, um,
yeah, another circumstance that might
require human oversight is if you're in
like scenarios where you could make safe
like safety critical mistakes. Like, uh,
if you are, um, a legged robot, you can
like fall in a way that damages the
robot. Uh, if you're a manipulator, you
could like drop a like glass onto the
floor. You could also like hit objects
um, pretty hard. the there's actually
work that um
that builds very directly upon some of
these ideas where you actually try to
learn learn some notion of safety and
learn when you're actually in a
high-risisk state and then go back to a
state that is less risky. So you could
actually learn for example like a
recovery policy that tries to get back
to states that you are are known to be
less risky and and and more safe. Um and
so these ideas actually some of these
ideas actually were um were actually
like uh several years ago studied in
sort of safety settings. Um [snorts] the
other practical thing to do is to try to
the extent possible um try to impose
safety constraints on the controller
itself uh so that for example you're not
um using the motors to the to the point
in which they'll overheat uh or minimize
like have a box around the robot that
doesn't allow it to for example um like
apply a lot of force to uh different
parts of the state space. Now, that's
not possible everywhere and learning
notions of safety uh might be the only
way to actually kind of address the
problem in general. Although to learn
safety, you need examples of of failing.
So, it's generally a a pretty tricky
problem. Um and yeah, I guess those are
my main thoughts on that. Yeah. Uh so
you could also the question is maybe you
could um when navigating around people
you could try to um ask a VLM like uh
like what you might try to do like at
high level in different circumstances
and this um this this work right here
actually was using a VLM to like
indicate w with past experience what are
good strategies to try. Uh and so um
these models may have some sort of
common sense suggesting like maybe you
shouldn't like walk or run into a person
for example um and or maybe you should
wait that sort of thing. Uh and so
leveraging those that that sort of
common sense um in those models uh is
like fairly promising.
Cool. Um great. So to summarize, we
talked about uh why reinforcement
learning algorithms don't already give
robots autonomous learning capabilities.
um and kind of defined the problem,
defined a couple instances of this
problem where we either want to think
about uh like the lifetime of rewards or
learning a good policy. Um and we talked
about algorithms for each of those uh
where we try to for example learn a
backward policy, learn a task graph um
and try different tasks and also single
life RL to prevent drift.